{
  "reference_number": "12269",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": "The most urgent action is required. 2050 may be too late, but it appears to be the fastest target that is politically feasible without a\n dictatorship or a centrally planned economy (eg China). So, lets make it bold, binding and unambiguous. Businesses will stop fighting\n\n climate action once the inevitability of their future translation sets in, and it becomes a race to the future."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": "The boldest target please. New Zealand is a small part of the global problem, but we can show bold political and moral leadership and\n inspire and motive campaigns in the larger polluters. We did it with our anti nuclear stance, lets do it with climate."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "I have seen no persuasive evidence that a global regulator can possibly ensure the integrity of internationally traded carbon credits\n\n with bullet proof audibility, continuously for the next 50 years. We should sort our own house, in our own borders, and seek to\n become _the_ high integrity exporter of excess carbon credits. As a rich OECD nation, with abundant renewable energy options and\n low population density we should be racing Iceland to be at the head of the pack."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "We should embed a ratchet clause to allow the goals to become faster and more aggressive if scientific evidence continues to\n\n accumulate the the climate crisis is even more urgent that currently believed."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "No - emissions budgets should not be able to be changed",
      "answer_index": 9,
      "notes": "The Climate commission should set the budget based on science. Politicians are notoriously bad at the discipline of long term\n planning for long term benefit. The Climate commission should have the ability to ratchet the carbon budget tighter, but never to\n\n loosen it."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "The Climate commission should set the budget based on science. Politicians are notoriously bad at the discipline of long term\nplanning for long term benefit. The Climate commission should have the ability to ratchet the carbon budget tighter, but never to\nloosen it."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Markets alone cannot achieve our emissions goals. Direct government intervention will be needed for society wide systems such as\n\nenergy and transport. Farming will need massive financial government support to achieve a transition in time."
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "1. Accelerate the move to 100% renewable electricity. Its small, but symbolic. This will require direct government intervention via bans\non thermal generation, splitting up the gentailers by government purchase of the generation assets and government sale of the retail\n\narms, and possibly capitalising the generators by direct government funding of consented but unbuilt wind generation. 2. 100% zero\nemissions land transport. We need to accelerate this by a) Government sanctioned monopoly of the public fast charging network\n\n(either PPP or SOE) b) A generous \"feebate\" scheme for light electric vehicles, c) electrification of 100% of the rail system, d) moving\nsignificant volumes of heavy freight off the roads onto rail."
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Makes decisions itself in respect of the number of units available in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 10,
      "notes": "Politicians are not good long term custodians. They will find reasons they need to be \"expedient\" or \"practical\", and water down the\ntargets \"just for a year or 2 until the economy can recover\". This is not acceptable. Physics does not care about election campaigns."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "This is a related but separate challenge. It needs different thinking, expertise and political framing. Lets land the Zero Carbon Bill as a\n\nmitigating instrument first, then have the adaptation conversation."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    }
  ]
}
